hello and welcome everyone it's November
16th 2023 we're in acin live stream
55.2 and it's our second discussion with
Magnus here on the message passing
papers in this dot two we're going to
begin with some code
Explorations see where it goes and then
in the last section have more open
discussion and see where that goes so
thank you for joining again Magnus and
looking forward to seeing this
code yeah thanks uh thanks for having me
so yeah one of the things we we talked
about last time um was that it would be
nice to go through what all this Theory
actually looks like in code so I brought
along something that I prepared uh
earlier which is basically the
experiments uh that go with the paper
papers and I think the one that makes
the most sense to look at is the one
where we do direct policy inference
because that's sort of one of the really
novel things where we don't encapsulate
uh PRI algorithms we we actually get
something
new so that is uh what we hopefully have
on screen right now all of this is
implemented in Julia and it is all
publicly available so like for anyone
who's interested you can you can go and
mess around with this on your own if you
want but basically the model we're going
to be looking at is the same discret pum
DP that we all know and love but instead
of uh Computing expected free energes
and comparing them to finding our to
find our policy we're just going to
infer the policy in one go as part of
optimization uh so would it make sense
if I just go through it cell by cell
or yeah maybe make the font a little
bigger and and then go sell by sell yeah
perfect thank you all right this better
yeah sweet so all of this in Julia um
and runs the notebooks there's um yeah
instructions for for how to do it and
the repo so the first thing we do is we
just load a bunch of things that we
need uh these here are all message
passing rules for the transition mixture
model the transition mixture model is
what allows us to do policy difference
it's basically saying instead of having
one transition Matrix one B
Matrix we have a number of candidate
ones and then we have a variable that
just picks
one so let's say I have either one
transition Matrix or another transition
Matrix if my indicator variable is 1 Z I
pick this one if it is 01 I pick this
one that's sort of the logic
here then we have this goal observation
node which is a goal constrained
observation node and this is where we do
uh the GV based message passing so this
is where we have the P substitutions
going on that we talked about last time
and where we get to get all our
epistemics and then we have like a bunch
of healthful functions to set up PRI for
stuff
whatever uh so what this code implements
is the teamas
experiment and again I think we all we
all know how the teammates works but
just for
completeness
sake uh actually I think I might be able
to pull up the paper and show the
graphic for the teamas because then we
can see exactly what it is for modeling
we can see how that corresponds to the
graph and everything just give me two
seconds I'll do
that uh here we
go so this is the teammate
environment um and this is the reaper
where you can find the code
in the teammate environment the agent
starts in one of four positions which
Rel
one and in it's designed to simulate a
rat looking for cheese in a maze there's
a reward at either positions two or
three so either know one of these
arms the main point is the agent doesn't
know which arm has the um the reward at
to learn that it needs to go to position
four position four has a que that tells
it whether the arm is uh the the r is
likely to be to the left or to the
right this means we need four
transitions want to go to States 1 2 3
and
four uh and then we need a um a
likelihood Matrix that sort of maps to
different observations that we can get I
where are we at L location do we get a
reward that kind of thing from all these
uh four different
locations so I think I actually have
yeah so I can actually show the the
constraint FFG of the model that we're
building and it looks like
this so what's going on here is that we
have a vector D that parameterizes where
we start that says this
prior then we have this transition
mixture
node the transition just from a laden
State at time T to time t plus one it
has four candidate transition matrices
again because we need to move to either
one two three or four and then we we
have this indicator variable uh that we
call U and that just picks whether we go
to 1 two 3 or
four down here is where we have the uh
to me the really interesting bit because
this is where we perform this P
substitution you can see here we have a
meanfield factorization and a p
substitution and we have uh this
composite node this goal observation
node with a goal
prior so what this says is um do
GV based optimization around this
note and the goal is is given by this
categorical down here so it's going to
have some C Vector that parameterizes it
this same kind of notation you're going
to find in most of the
papes and we're going to infer a
two-step policy so we need to go from
initial Point ZT to T plus1 to T plus2
think I should need to put T plus2 in
here but no
matter uh
this does this model and this graph make
sense perfect like the thing that I want
to sort of point out is that we can see
all these things where we do the E based
things uh the kind of messages that we
need to pass the factorizations all of
this is something that we can see from
the graph because this a constrainted
FFG uh instead of a normal
FFG so let's look at what this little
guy looks like in code
code uh and it looks like this so we
have a
categorical uh with a d Vector that
starts we have C which is going to be
our goal
PRI we have our Laten States and we have
our indicator
variables each indicator variable gets a
flat prior that's what this do yeah so
for for all time steps I for all future
time steps want to plan over we need an
indicator variable with a flat prior so
we are a priority indifferent as to
which state we want to go
to we have um a transition mixture that
maps from
oops Z at the previous time
step so Z at the current time step
G um and it takes us input the indicator
variable or
switch and our candidate the transition
matrices we have the same thing we the
next note which is this gold constraint
observation
node has a likelihood
Matrix i e this
oops a
here and a goal uh prior which is the C
here see
see input from the state
and the um the likelihood Matrix and
this here is some um Plumbing that we
need to uh get the messages to work out
so don't don't worry too much about
this and this is actually the the model
specification this is all there is to
it um which to me is kind of nice
because if we can do inference in the
back end then if I want to build mods
and with design agents all I really they
need should be able to should have to
worry about um is to set up my model
specification
correctly all
right uh right this is another a little
bit of Plumbing um and these are like
optional constraints that we are going
to introduce later what this basically
says is that we want to Point Mass
constrain
um the the switch variables the
indicators so instead of saying um I'm
sort of indifferent between going to two
and three and put equal probability on
them we're forcing the agent to make a
choice we're saying you can only pick
one and this is identical to having
a point Mass constraint or a Delta
constraint as described in part one
that's what this thing
does uh right so then let's set up
everything we need we have a planning
Horizon of two we want to run uh 10 INF
iterations because this uh optimization
procedure is an iterative
thing uh that we also need to set some
initial marginals like a VMP thing and
we need to construct our a b c and d
matrices uh which for those of you that
had worked with pmtp or SPM or similar
these work the exact same
way uh and then all we need to do is
call the inference function
function with you know the model with
all our parameters so theage model we
just defined with our a
b matrices our D vectors to start within
our time Horizon
C we set our goal prior as data
inputs which is just a convenience thing
we did to make life a little easier sort
of
programmatically um and then then We're
Off to the
Races
so let's actually see what happens when
we run this so if you just load
everything should be up to date in a
minute
here yeah so let's uh create a
model create our
constraints configure our
experiment and now we are here so we can
run
inference so do you have any guess as to
uh how long long is this going to
take 11
miston it's pretty
accurate so it actually takes a little
bit the first time because the model
needs to be compiled now you can see we
have new posteriors available for our
switch variable our state variables and
our initial State
variable so let's see what we got so
what we're printing here is just the um
distribution the posterior Marg over the
indicator variable I.E the probability
of choosing go to one go to two go to
three or go to
four and what we get is
uh this long number that we around to
about 25% chance of going to
four about 20% chance of going to either
two or three and 35% chance of going to
four that
means quarter of the time I just as much
as we put in our price
we're staying
put about 20% of the time the agent
wants to go and explore either arm
because I mean there's still reward
there and the most likely option uh with
a grand 35 uh probability is that we
should go and investigate the
que so go to position
four if we then compare what that looks
like at uh T equals 2 that is what does
the agent believe it should do after the
first time step so if it goes in this is
the queue what should it do
next here we see that it is quite
unlikely to stay put uh sorry to go to
um to the starting position doesn't
probability there it's coming from the
prior it is indifferent between going to
either two or three because even though
we know that we're going to get
information at Q we still don't know
whether it is going to be right or
left and that's represented here by
these two being you know equally
valuable um however combined it means we
have about a 60% chance of going to uh
to an arm which is probably going to be
the right
one and then with about again the
quarters about what we put into the
prior probability we're going to go and
look at the queue
again
and this is the same result yeah yeah so
as you pointed out one of the big
contributions here is this direct policy
inference so let's just say that we have
the probabilities of different state
occupancies at time one and time two
yeah but how do we really retain the
fullness of a path for
example um time one and time two might
not
be jointly independent
so for example um yeah the probability
of being at the Q in the at time one and
time two might not be just. 35 time
026 no no so what what this is uh I
think we can take a look at
this see this actually was
here uh like just just to clarify the
question while you're typing it um if
we're not explicitly tracing the
branching
Paths of specific sequences of states
and rather we're
getting over each time step then how do
we know that just because something is
10% likely on here and 10% likely there
but then that doesn't mean it's one in
100 together that those both happen it
might be more or less depending on how
the paths actually flow right so the
thing is here we're inferring a
distribution over possible
futures um so we don't have any
observations available we don't actually
have a full action perception Lo we're
just doing
planning um and since we don't have any
observations available the best we can
do is get a distribution over all the
different possible features that we have
now we could do that but get that by
like an exhaustive search say I want
this and I say this this probability or
we could just infer
it so
what this tells us uh is not like it's
not a sophisticated scheme it doesn't
have sort of the counterfactual thing
going on what it tells us is that if we
want to
optimize
um this combination of Bey and
generalized free
energy expected free
energy uh before we get any observations
what is the optimal distribution over
paths that we could take
okay so the t2
distribution is basically T2
distribution as viewed from
t0 yes and then when we get to T1 we'll
update but we're basically taking uh
something like a mean field or an
aggregate over all possible paths to
T2 and those May radically shift like
obviously once we go to the queue and
find out some information then
okay yeah yeah so this is this is at T
equals zero this is the agent saying
well if I have to make a decision right
now for the whole game for all my time
steps for my whole plan what is sort of
the the most likely thing that I should
do and how should that distribute itself
once we actually start to get
observations in there um then then yeah
these are obviously going to shift yeah
then it's very
notable that the two arms do have
this High quantity taken together but
absolutely equal it's and that's that
kind of like being precise about
uncertainty that we would want such a
planner to have yeah exactly what what
this is saying is the agent is really
confident that it needs to go to one of
the arms but because it hasn't got an
observation because it hasn't actually
seen the queue yet it doesn't know which
one so it assigns them equal
probability but it is pretty I'm sure
that it needs to go to one of
them which again makes sense if we think
of this as doing planning at T equals
zero yeah it's it's really cool like
especially after so much expected free
energy branching time active inference
exhausted searches just to see this kind
of non path-based direct policy
inference that's the contribution of the
paper yeah I mean I would say this is
closer to a path-based formulation what
you don't get is a search
tree thank you thank you yes consistent
with the path-based formulation of
basing mechanics but not necessarily
resulting in an exhaustive search tree
exactly so what what we can actually do
here is we can look at the
schedule what's going on here so this
this actually shows us the exact uh way
that messages are flowing under the hood
in the code
and the main thing that's different to
most other approaches is that we have
things flowing backwards we have these
red guys here and we have these here
flowing in the opposite direction so
this information flowing from what we
think the future is going to be
towards what the present is and what
this is telling us um is given that I
want to end up here and I reent
backwards what should I
do and that is why we don't need a
search street because instead of having
to run
forwards we can do the forward sweep
here say well this is my distribution
over things that I'm going to do if I
don't know
anything and in the other direction we
have well this is distribution over what
you should do a why expect to end
up and if you have where you expect to
be and where you expect to end up
figuring out what to
do is is like what what what happens
here and that's how you do the the
policy
it's because you have an idea of where
you're going to be and you have an idea
of where you want to end up if you know
those then inferring what you should do
is at least in these simple cases quite
straightforward and again sort of the
one of the contributions here is that
because we do this backwards smoothing
sweep we don't have to do a a forward
search
tree because around usually these notes
all we have to do is care about we care
about a message flowing in Here We Care
message flowing in here and
then we can do our inference it also
means that every time we add a time step
if I were to take uh this wait this guy
here and extend it once more to the
right I wouldn't have to like an
exponential explosion I would have to
evaluate the messages flowing around
inside one of these sort of slices once
more so we need another backwards
message another backwards message
another forwards
message
and that's sort of where um one of the
things I want to do that we didn't get
around to doing for these papers is to
investigate how this behaves when we
scale to longer Horizons and larger
models because this should scale uh much
nicer than having to do an exhaustive
search treat because every time we add
um another
slice we just add the same number of
computations
again
right so let's go back here right so
what we do here in the last
experiment uh is that we add these Point
Mass constraints to the switch
variables so what does this yeah so on a
graph it looks like
this this the exact same graph but now
we add these little constraints here
these little delta form constraints in
the
beads and this means that when we
compute our posterior here it has to to
be a
Delta so we need to pick one of the
options we can't say I'm indifferent
between going right or left you have to
pick
one because you have to be a Delta
Spike so in practice this ends up being
the same as taking the agmax of
um the distribution over over actions so
you're effectively as part of your
inference procedure picking the best
policy and doing inference only with the
most like
thing so let's run
that and again this gives us a much sort
of clearer picture where we are now 100%
certain that we're going to go to the Q
at T equals one before we observe
anything and then in this case it picks
two but if you change the random seat a
little bit it picks three because it's
it's IND different between these two
guys it just has to pick one because
we're enforcing
that
yeah it's it's still at t0 speculating
it and so it's kind of like
a a
bifurcation where depending on its
random seed at t0 it might symmetry
break to imagine it going left or
imagine going right in that
implementation but either way after T1
it's going to have the
empirical
decision exactly I might actually be
able to show this as well
if we do this so part two actually has
an example of the kind of
protocol where we have these this is the
thing I want to show we have these
updates going
on this this one reminded me this one
reminded me of the fire escape plan of a
hotel I didn't think of that but I can
actually see
it so effec what's different between
these experiments and the ones we just
looked at is um that these U's here are
clamped the little black squares and P
that means we are picking a transition
Matrix so we are fixing whatever our
transition should
be and this here T equals 1 is before uh
the agent observes anything so this
effectively the same situation we just
looked that except now we are evaluating
a policy we're doing the same search
tree kind of thing uh instead of doing
direct policy
inference so again these are just
Transitions and these appear fixed so
we're no longer doing direct policy
inference we're just uh Computing the uh
free energy including GV terms for this
model without any
observations and the thing I want to
sort of point out is these composite
noes down here is that the exact same
that we just
had um but you see there's nothing going
on here like these X variables have
nothing on them but once we get an
observation it's the same as adding this
constraint down here so we advance the
time step it goes from one to
two and then we clamp our observation
and then we do the same protocol again
because the model hasn't changed what's
changed is that we constrain one of the
variables to be equal to our
observation and then you keep on going T
equals 2 and so on and so forth every
time you get a new observation you just
add these
little uh constraints to the
model this and then you'll get yeah this
reminds me of scientific
pre-registration like we have the whole
experimental plan laid out we know what
kind of information is going to flow in
and we have a distrib distribution or
prior over the data and then when the
data do come in we just
clamp the format that we expected and we
don't need to do any structural changing
to the factor graph and so it's like as
we're moving forward and collecting data
we're just clamping timelines on the
past and then leaving open what hasn't
happen slash what we don't know yeah
that that's exactly what's happening um
like beautifully but because ex that's
exactly what's happening as we get data
but just saying well now I know that
this variable in my graph that
corresponds to my observation
I didn't know what it was before but now
I know that it was this value so I need
to put that observation into my my
inference problem somehow my model is
still the same doesn't change the
structure of how I think the world works
like parameters might have shifted and
stuff
but like the main thing that's changed
is that I now have a data point that I
need to add in and you can do that by
adding these little um yeah data
constraints we call them so this here
actually shows the exact type of thing
that you were uh just talking about how
does the model change once we get data
points so this case here would be pure
sort of speculation pure planning ahead
of time and this here is well once you
start observing stuff how do you
actually add the information into your
uh your inference
problem yeah one other angle on this
again because I think this is really
important the structure here is kind of
like the Timeless action perception Loop
and then we can be anywhere from at the
top we have purely speculative purely
anticipatory on the bottom we have
purely retrospective all the data are
already in hand and it's kind of like a
solved issue like looking at a a
something that already played out or you
could be kind of the inmedia res in the
middle between which is basically just
to say that part of it is already
clamped in with the past and then part
of it is speculative and all of those
settings from like the purely
anticipatory to the purely retrospective
to in the middle of things with a little
bit of both all those are structurally
described by the
same
formalism yeah um and again that's
because the model doesn't change what
changes is just we need to add
in the data now what what is kind of
nice about this is that it also allow
you to talk about doing different things
at different
times um so one thing that we for
instance looked at is once we have all
the data should we do our parameter
updates then because you can imagine a
situation where you run an episode of
something that you are trying to do some
psychophysics uh experiment and you have
your uh participant run you know an
entire episode of an experiment and then
you expect them to go and update their
beliefs about say uh some parameters for
what occurs
where you can model that by saying one
once all my observations are clamed then
I send messages toward my parameters my
thetas down
here so this sort of highlights the the
kind of things that you can start to be
very very explicit
about when do you do certain updates
what should the graph the constraints
look
like um all these things that um kind of
often has a tendency to sort of get
swept under the rock a little bit that
you can now be like very very explicit
about yeah that's super important again
keeping with this theme of kind of like
looking forward Looking Back Being able
to plan out the message passing
Logistics and scheduling means that you
can have a sense of the computational
requirements and so on forward-looking
and then also looking back
have a better sense of the way that
variables were generated and Trace back
their kind of informational supply chain
so that this is that's what makes it
fully synthetic if it were fully
synthetic chemical we could trace from
the precursors how it were generated
this is fully synthetic active inference
agent and so that means for every
variable we should be able to say well
here's how we brought it onto the table
and then here's exactly how the messages
were passed from once it was placed yeah
like what what is the model what is the
inference problem what is the data and
what are the constraints that's that's
like we should have everything be
completely
transparent um because that's that's in
my opinion that's good uh the more you
know we're allow scrutiny of all the
little different bits and pieces and the
more we can investigate how everything
is going on um like the the
better and this is kind of the ground
floor like you could keep digging and
ask well how is addition carried out how
is multiplication carried out in Julia
or how however but this is kind of the
layer that is the foundation layer for
building then more elaborate graphs like
we don't need to finer scale or do we
that that's actually kind of funny right
because each of these messages we're
drawing those just as arrows but each of
these messages uh is a computation right
you mentioned that you need to do a
multiplication like one thing we need to
do for these models we also do for for
this thing here is we need to multiply
um a categorical variable by a uh
transition
Matrix that is an INF that is an
operation that is a message so there's a
whole computation and a whole derivation
that you can go and and
find uh for how to do that
operation so everything
is uh should be completely transparent
here yeah all right I'll ask a question
from the live chat Andrew writes okay if
the model is
CL stop the screen share oh no it's fine
it's fine I'll just ask it here yeah if
the model is clamped in this manner how
does the generative model evolve is
there a way that new variables can be
introduced during the inference
generative
Loop right so that's a thing that's
actually quite uh interesting and the
short answer is not with this uh
formalism there is some like nice work
on structure learning and how to like do
Bas model comparison Bas model reduction
and expansion that you could use in in
this context but as is what we've done
is we've found a way to write down a
model and an inference problem and the
the corresponding messages that allow
you to do um GF based optimization it
doesn't tell you how to expand your
model now again uh if you want to
combine this with something like Bas and
model reduction or expansion uh that
would be cool I think someone should
should really go and do that because
that would be an interesting sort of
Avenue to go down when we can start to
combine these things and one of the sort
of things that I wanted out of these uh
these two papers is that I wanted to be
able to get this kind of thing
explicit right I wanted to to have a
language that um is not too difficult to
pick
up that allows people to ask these kinds
of
questions because there's a very
different um at least in in my mind I
don't know whether you agree Andrew but
to me there's sort of a different vibe
to philosophically thinking about what
does the model evolve like and saying
well how do I add a
node one is a very concrete problem that
you can start to talk about while the
other can be very sort of can end up
being very very abstract if you if you
let it I like things that are concrete
and and transparent so I'm really glad
that this kind of question pops up
because that's one of the things that I
wanted to to do with these papers is to
get people thinking along these lines
awesome I I'll kind of give another
angle on that question so there's a
implicit or unprincipled or ad hoc
strategy here which would be we're going
to be operating our model and then we're
going to have some extracurricular
diagnostic like if it's taking too long
we're going to um then we're going to do
something else outside of the generative
model and change a generative model like
oh maybe we should add another variable
so that's kind of like the nonpr
principled approach of which there's an
infinite amount of these types and they
may or may not be documented in the
paper whereas the principled approach
would be to bring that structural
learning that learning structure
explicitly in through basian structuring
so then you could say okay well there's
either one two or three factors in this
regression and then we're going to have
a distribution prior over whether
there's one two or three factors and
then we're going to claim lamp
eventually and find the best fitting
model whether it is 1 2 or three with
the appropriate um penalization and then
someone says well what if there's four
it's like great now we're going to
explicitly bring that possibility into
the model so that we have a unified
approach to talking about the kind of
sensory motor lower level parameters and
arbitrary nestings of structure learning
those shouldn't be outside the perimeter
of the fully synthetic agent
otherwise to the extent that it's
outside the perimeter the engineering
perimeter it's out of
control yeah I think we we at least um I
think we should be a little bit wary
about what we uh attribute to the agent
and what we attribute to the engineer
here because when we set this this
approach up an agent is just you know a
graph where that that you receives some
observations and allowed to emit some
actions um so there is still an
engineering aspect here about how do you
construct the graph what should the
graph like what should the model look
like um which is not addressed in these
papes but you absolutely right there
should be a a principled way of doing
that which something like Bas model
comparison um is is a way to
do um but the agent I the graph that
does inference just does inference on
the
graph at least with the tools that are
in here you would need to add some
something more to do like organically
growing graph or
something does the graph ever undergo
structural Evolution or does the
structure of the graph change but then
through clamping and parameter updating
the graph can even with a fixed topology
represent structural differences or do
are there ever
actual structural changes in the factor
graph so I think that's one of the nice
um things about the the CFG approach to
writing down
models is that you can write like you
need two things to do to minimize free
energy function you need a p and a q
that's what you need to write
at um and writing p is done with
standard Factor graph notation so you
write out your boxes and your edges and
sort of you construct your graph your
model and the constraints and the done
in
Q that is um you write them separately
so you can talk about what happens in
terms of constraints and what happens in
terms of the structure of the graph sort
of separately and
explicitly um so the graph uh at least
what we've done here doesn't uh sort of
intrinsically undergo any um like
topological iCal structural changes it's
just the model you write down that you
as as an engineer as a scientist is
interested
in uh what you can change is you can
change the
constraints that allows you to to do
different things with the same model for
instance incorporate data points as your
agent sort of progresses through
time um but what you can do then with
this type of notation is you can be
explicit you can be explicit about when
you're doing something with the
constraints of the model on the model
sorry constraints on the inference
problem I should say where you're
defining your q and when you're doing
something structurally with the
generator model when you're defining
your P because one is done in terms of
this like bead overlay notation and the
other one is done with standard sort of
factor graph
methodologies um so what what in that
context what's the the main advantage of
these two papers is is that you can be
explicit about what you're
doing yes very
interesting yeah I hope so continue with
the code here
yeah uh yeah I mean we've actually
reached the end of The Notebook uh this
is all that is to the policy inference
experiments but one of the things that
you can do with this type of thing if we
go back to the generative model
specification
um is that this
here uh is just defined in terms of noes
and
edges I I have my variables and I have
my notes that Define them and I have my
uh goal observation where do the P
substitutions and
everything um but these
units like they're sort of atomic in
nature all a node cares about is Zone
Mark of
blanket so these things are composable
meaning that if you want to build them
with say hierarchies or heterarchies you
want to add multiple modalities all
these kinds of things you could might
want to
do um that still
works s of with a caveat that you know
there might be some coding bugs and
stuff you run into because it's still
just still software after all but
theoretically once you have these
different things as little building
blocks you can sort of Lego your way
through to any
model something that we hint at in the
papers as well that we um they're not
really sort of explored in the in the
experiments which is that this type of
uh active inference works for free form
generative
models that means because it's local all
the little changes we do are local on
the graph everything else can just be
whatever it wants to
be so so you're no longer limited to
using a pomdp model which is an awesome
model like there's loads of things you
can do with it it's a great
model um but there are things that might
be easier to do like operate with
continuous variables for
instance uh that might be easier to do
with a different type of model and if
you can sort of Lego block your way to a
generative model that uh represents how
you think uh your agent should think
that the world
operates and that is that is something
you can now
do because model model sort of space has
become much much
larger right there with the how you
think an agent should
think is the articulation between the
engineer and the
agent that's the second level inference
problem the first level inference
problem is what the synthetic artifact
will be doing in its runtime and then
the engineering question is how to
create that and so it's almost like the
engineer is only interfacing with the
inference challenge or environment
through the blanket of the fully
synthetic
agent yeah and that's in my opinion
that's how it it should be I guess if I
put on my my engineer hat for a
um I'm a lace
engineer like I I can go to if I have a
problem to solve I could go to the
literature and I could find you know 57
Solutions and I could pick one and I can
implement it three a bit and now I have
58 Solutions that's one way I can do it
I have several solutions for every
problem that becomes unwieldy real quick
because every problem you have like bat
load of
solutions um what I like to do is say I
want only one tool I can only do
inference I believe that everything can
be solved by inference if you set up the
problem
right and the trick then is how do you
set up the problem
right so as an engineer what I would
sort of take from this um way of of
approaching approaching
problems is that my task is to build a
generative model that does the thing
that I wanted to do
and there's going to be some iterations
and trial and error and some tweaking of
things and all these nice sort of
practical challenges that that we all uh
run into when we try to actually build
things um but the tool should always be
the same if I want to control a robot or
um track an object uh or localization or
preference learning or filter an audio
signal or whatever you might want to do
the tool should always be the
same all I should should need to do is
do
inference it's my job as the engineer to
figure out what is the model structure
um that produces the the results that I
want because it's clear if I want to say
move a robot arm and I have a you know a
generative model that can only move to
the right I'm going to run into
issues now again you sort of also hint
that there's an an extra level that you
can go to uh where it becomes about
structure learning now you you want to
learn the structure of the model you
want to learn P you want to sort of
build your graph
organically um which would be amazing to
solve but uh I'm not going to claim that
that we're anywhere near there with
these papers these papers is just a way
to accurately write down what I as the
engineer want to
happen
is there any more code you want to
show um we can take a look at the other
ones
uh but they they basically work the same
way so this is for um generalized free
energy with an action perception Loop
I.E and and a fixed policy this
simulates the kind of things you would
get in something like pmtp
usbm
excuse
me so again the um setup here is very
very
similar Define our model which has um a
policy that we want to
evaluate uh it has two time steps has
our goal priors it has our initial State
prior um but now we're also interested
in learning the parameters of our
observation Matrix so we put a prior a
durly prior over our a matrix over our
likelihood
Matrix and otherwise these here move
like they they look very much the same
it's instead of mixture models over
transitions it's just fixed
transitions uh and this here is calling
the exact same um sort of P substituted
mean field constraint all that goodness
node that we used for the last uh like
the direct policy INF
simulations
uh and then we do the same
thing we load up our PRI we load up our
matrices and because we want
to repeat this over and over and over
and over we're actually going to run an
agent for 100 episode so it's going to
play the game a 100 times and try to
learn the um the likelihood
Matrix and does so by inferring an
action as doing infin missing in the
model taking an action executing it in
the environment here and here and then
getting back an observation and this
getting an observation does this
clamping operation that we talked
about so this is literally the thing
that's shown here T equals z t equals T
1 tals 2 and in this case T equals 3
because that's how many steps is in the
T
environment
sorry and if we do that and we run this
uh 100 times oh yeah so every time the
agent has completed an episode so it's
done it's it's two steps it gets to send
messages towards the parameters a it
gets to learn about the uh the a matrix
the likelihood of the
um of the observations given the
states and if we do that we can look at
the differences from the sort of very
flat prior that it gets
initially uh versus the end posterior
PRI end posteriors to look at what has
this agent
learned the way to sort of read read
this plot um is that o refers to the
origin location so location one in the
uh like in this thing here
oops Yeah location one in this thing
here it's the
origin we have the left arm and the
right arm L and R and we have C the Q
location RW means reward and you get a
reward NR means no
reward and this here says is the reward
to the left the reward to the
right um Q points left Q points right
what we can see here is that nothing
really happens in the origin
State we always moving so we don't
really get
much
um we can see if we on the left
arm and the Q points to the left and the
reward is also on the left
arm we are pretty likely to observe a
reward if the reward is on the left
we're likely to observe a reward if go
to the
left same thing over here the reward is
on the right pretty likely to observe a
reward on the
right the interesting thing up here uh
so what happens at the Q location right
because this says that if the Q points
to the left the reward is also pretty
likely to be on the left if the Q points
to the right the reward is also pretty
lik to be on the right so this shows us
that if we do this iteration the agent
can actually
learn um the like a pretty good we're
going to say the correct but like a
really good um likelihood Matrix that
predicts where things are and how all
the relations actually work in the tmas
experiment which is nice because that
means that we uh we don't have to put
all this in we can actually do parameter
learning using this GV based message
pausing as well which is really
neat
and here we have some uh free energy
curves so this shows the free energy at
the initial time
step so before any observations have
been
received all right yeah and when the uh
first observation has been received and
then after the second observation has
been received and we do parameter
learning and you'll see everything get
like nice and decreasing but there are
these spikes
here and these spikes indicate
when the agent predicts a win but gets a
loss so the agent the Q says the uh
rewards to the left the agent goes to
the right there to the left but it
doesn't get a reward there's a bit of
stochasticity in the teammates
environment um so it's not always 100%
sure even if you que points the right
way and everything that the agent
actually gets a reward observation in
the
end and this to me is is pretty nice
because it shows that if um the agent's
predictions are
violated we can actually directly see
that in the in the free energy of the
model we get these sort of prediction
error
spikes which I think is is really
nice um we have a similar setup which
completely identical except we don't do
the S A P substitution we don't
introduce a gve term we just run Bo
standard uh rational Bey free energy
minimization and the model looks the
same we just uh use like some Bey
options for uh this composite node what
is
meta So Meta is a way this all done in
RX and
fur meta is a way to pass options to a
node um and in this case the Bey meta
tells um this sort of joint node
composed of a likelihood model and a
goal
prior whether it should uh optimize
generalized free energy or battery free
energy so you can think of it as if we
look at the graph
again and if you had this note here to
make this a little
bigger we have this sort of composite
note here inside the dash
lines there's a difference between if we
draw a circle here or we draw a
square square would indicated we do a p
substitution which turns this locally
into a generalized free
energy if we don't do that we draw a
circle don't do the P substitution what
we're left with is a mean field
factorized Bethy free
energy and the way we do uh this s
switch between a circle and a square is
through this meta
object you also use it for other things
for other nodes and arer like if you
have um say a nonlinear function that
you want to use somewhere in your graph
you want to pass messages through it
again need to do some approximations
most of the time so you can say pass
your approximation method uh through the
meta object and if you know run some
iterations or you need to do some
sampling or something that kind of
information is something you can feed in
through the meta
object so what this thing is really
saying is just swap uh like the square
for a
circle so that we do bir free energy
instead of generalized free
energy and then everything else here is
exactly the same this is literally a
copy paste of the the other
notebook because again we're not
changing the model we're just messing
with the constru
the model is the same all we're doing is
messing with the constraints and the P
substitution and if we instead of saving
the figures actually create
these yeah you'll see this agent only
gets uh
stuff like around the the outcome
because it starts with uninformative uh
PRI over the a
matrix doesn't really know what the
reward is there's no incentive to go and
explore it just doesn't really
accomplish
much you can see the same thing free
energy is flatlining nothing is
happening and it is consistently not
performing well it is uh it just endured
a 100 trials of loss and I don't think
it is particularly enjoying
itself and again so the the thing that
we can illustrate with this um is the
power of messing with uh constraints and
messing with P substitutions and messing
with these sort of local adaptations to
the free
energy because the model in both cases
the P the graph is actually the same
there's no
difference the thing that's different
here is we're messing with the
constraints and we are messing with uh
turning this local Bey free energy into
a local generalized free energy and that
produces these quite drastic changes in
in the behavior of the
agent yes the Bey free energy agent does
not do well here just changing that one
yeah aspect moves the
epistemic phenomena into the present
that's that kind of like EF like
component of the GFE that we discussed
last time yeah exactly so what what this
um thing
does basically if you if you do the B
free energy uh you end up with an agent
that does kale
control this ends up being a completely
standard uh control problem that
controls inference there's nothing
nothing fancy going on
here um and crucially that does not
include an epistemic component we get no
information seeking and we see that here
there's no information seeking anywhere
here
there little guys just
flatlining
um but once we start to mess with the
function that we introduce as epistemic
component we get exploration we get good
performance we get this active curiosity
information seeking all these nice
goodies that we know and love about
active inference
agents and we can show that very very
directly by simply saying well I'm going
to change this little circle to a
square
and then we have uh some aggregate
experiments that we also ran which is
just repeating the same thing over like
numbers of Agents because there's some
Stu as this to uh sometimes they get
reward sometimes they don't if you want
to compare
um yeah how this does sort of in the
aggregate you need to do multiple runs
I'm not going to run this because this
takes a long time to
run you see the I ran out earlier today
and it took like an hour and 20 minutes
um but what we can do is we can look at
the distribution over Wednesday how many
times per run does an agent obtain uh a
reward and you can see that it is very
much sort of
skewed to the right which is good that
means the agents learn they learn the
parameters and after they learn the
parameters they consistantly get uh
rewarded on their uh on their
trials doesn't always happen right there
a bit of sort of tail end down
here what this tells us is that
sometimes these agents um because there
STC casity in the rewards they're just
going to get stuck in some unfortunate
Minima they get some conflicting
information and they never quite managed
to
recover and that that can
happen sometimes you learn something
that's wrong and you sort of end up
sticking to
it uh so it's it's not a bulletproof
thing
uh the same thing here we can show this
is sort of the the ideal uh expected
reward you can get that as the trials
progress an average agent starts
learning earning more and more and more
and more reward how you get closer and
closer to this line there's some
wiggling in here that's because we have
to use a sampling approximation when we
send the message towards the parameters
so there's some stochasticity in here
which is why we get this bit of wiggling
that and and the reward stoas
this basically shows that as an
aggregate um agents get better they get
consistently
better but again the model is all the
same nothing
changes cool good with a
code yeah I don't I don't have any more
code uh not for the for these paps at
least cool yes thank you then
so I'll stop the screen
[Music]
share okay I'll um share screen um I
guess just to sort of transition into
this second component like when you sit
down at the
table where do you
begin um usually I begin where I left
off the day before
uh that's worked for uh for quite a
while
now and so there are other things that
I'm working on right now um that I I
can't really talk about
yet but just as a general a general um
building your own generative model like
if you had a new fun nonproprietary
study where would you begin with Sketch
in out what to be on the road to to
working with it this way right so if oh
now get yeah so the first thing I would
do is that I would start drawing graphs
I would start drawing my my constrainted
fgs and see if I can figure out what is
the problem that I want to solve and
then get that real
accurate and that is not a trivial
exercise um because once you have your
model specification your inference
specification in
place then like the hard to me the hard
part is is
done because again if I put on my
engineer hat the main thing that I have
to do if I want to build an application
I want to solve something is that I have
to come up with the graph and I have to
uh you know come up with the constraints
that Define my inference uh
problem once I'm there I need to figure
out are there any parts of this problem
that I can can
solve is there a message that I need to
work out is there uh some approximation
that I need to figure out to to put in
there um and if so it's nice that's sort
of a like a research question on its own
quite
often
um but if there
isn't then the next thing I would do is
I would try and and run inference in my
model if she does this model actually
behave as I think it
does especially if you're in the game of
Designing active inference agents
uh sometimes these things have a mind of
their own uh there several reasons why
that could
be um it maybe your intuitions
about like the thing that you wrote down
uh don't actually quite hold up to to
how things manifest in the real world or
or there might be like bugs in your code
all these sort of very practical things
but once we're at this place
um like to me a lot of the heavy lifting
is
done because the hard part if you want
to build to me if I want to build
something is specifying the model
specifying the constraints and figuring
out to solve the inference problem once
I have that then everything else is sort
of implementation
details um actually funny story we had
this during uh the design of the
experiments uh that we just looked at so
if you look at the transition matrices
that we use
uh if you have
a the original teammates transition
matrices they let the agent get stuck in
positions two and
three that's sort of attracting stat
once you go there you can't go anywhere
else and the way that is done
practically is that the transition
Matrix sends you from state two to state
two whatever transition Matrix you CH
you
choose if you do that with our
setup that means you're allowed to send
backwards
messages
uh that say well if I pick action one
which is no go to state one and I'm
coming from state two I would also go to
state
two does that make
sense so then what's the issue or what
did that result in um the result is that
the agent starts inferring some very
very nonsensical policies um because
it'll say well I know the goal is at
position
three but I'm going to confidentally go
like pick the Matrix that corresponds to
go to one or go to four go to like
two and that's because all these things
all these matrices allow the reverse
mapping from say uh state two you think
the reward is to any of the other
states why is there no reverse
constraint
so I can put this because if you're
reasoning backwards you have to think
about how do your model run in reverse
and what does your transition mean mean
the other
direction and the way we solved this was
that we send uh we let every sort of
invalid transition send it back to the
beginning
so every
um yeah basically if you end up in one
of the the rewarding
arms uh every transition that you pick
is going to send you back to the STS
it's just going to reset the whole
episode and if you do that you get rid
of this problem of the backward message
not corresponding to your intuitions as
as an
engineer because we're designed this
thing to say well one Matrix is go to
one one Matrix go to two and so on so
forth
but the math doesn't really care about
our intuitions the math is is like does
what the math does just it's up to us to
make sure that we VIP things down
accurately okay just to kind of confirm
this so the initial strategy was you
used as kind of classical in pdps you
just had the state of reward be
absorbing
however it was almost like you could get
in but then you didn't want it to leave
with the absorbing state but you
actually you had like a ladder out with
the backwards message and that was
leading to some weird things so instead
you change it so that the reward State
brought you back to the
beginning essentially tucking in the end
of the trial to something like the
beginning of the next trial and then
that better cohered with intuitions
around how policy should be selected so
you can think of it also as the
backwards message saying um if I go here
where should I come
from so if you are in say the rewarding
arm where should you be coming
from and if you allow the rewarding arm
to map from itself to itself because you
make it
absorbing the agent can correctly that's
what you put in infer that it should be
coming from the the rewarding
arm when it is in the rewarding
arm yeah how do you how do you get a
million dollars step one start with a
million dollars exactly and that that's
not the kind of inference that we we
want our agents to
make it's right if you have a million
dollars the most likely way you got them
is that you had them a second before you
had more a second
before
at at least a million dollars a second
before but yeah that that that kind of
inflence is something that we want our
agents to to not do H and that's an
issue that doesn't at least for now sort
of research hadn't arised did not arise
when we only did the sort of forwards
roll out version because if you never
Reon backwards this kind of thing just
doesn't pop up but if it starts then you
need to consider this this kind of sort
of circular uh step one start with a
million dollars type of
reasoning is that an example of
something that that we ran into in the
course of this experiment where we were
pretty sure that you know everything was
sort of set up
correct and it was but the agent didn't
do like did not behave in the way we
anticipated and sort of how we wanted it
to behave so we had to go and look at
what what is actually happening not what
do we think is happening what is
actually happening when you sort of
start to look at the
code let me ask a related question from
the chat Ander
says what you are saying is there's no
conditional probability placed on where
the agent thinks it is when doing that
reverse
message uh is when I think is the
question is there a conditional
probability placed on the agent when it
is doing the reverse
message yes but it was conditioned on
the
future you're doing everything backwards
so it is condition sort of conditional
on where you should be in the
future you can think of sort of the the
forward roll out approach saying well if
I am here and I do this then I go here
and so on and so forth then you have
this large tree that sort of expands to
uh where you could go and then you look
at all the places you could go and say
well that one that's the one I
like you can also think of doing the
same I'm sort of um um approximating a
little bit because we don't actually do
so indries but you also think of doing
the same thing in Reverse right you can
say well if I am at if I have already
obtained everything that I want in my
life where is it most likely that I came
from and I say all right if I go one
step back where is it then most likely
that I came from and so on and so
forth and that distribution that kind of
logic uh is what we're doing with the
backwards paths so then when you have
the forwards path saying well this is
where I'm likely to end up the backwards
path saying well this is where I want to
go resing that difference is uh is what
you do when you infer the action you
have two messages colliding and they
spit out something towards your um your
action
variable yeah okay well that's making me
think about is we classically think
about new data coming in we're
conditioning on the the existing
conditions and then new observation
comes in things update so that's the
sort of March
forward then there there's this kind of
aspirational or fulfillment based
conditioning conditioning on not what
has been sedimented and brought forward
but conditioning on what is anticipated
or preferred and then yeah let's think
about the the um three time step case
where there's a clear last step and
there's a clear first step and they just
meet in the middle and it just like the
sort of um the conditioning from both
ends results in just this obvious
solution however also it could be more
ambiguous at the beginning of the end or
it could be more than three time steps
and then that's where we get this um
message passing and kind of
annealing as data are getting clamped
through time and that has
a relationship with the search tree
based methods in that like the territory
of what they're explaining is the same
sequences of action but again to be
really clear this is not
doing policy specific evaluations
followed by comparison of expected free
energies or any kind of enumerative
search at all it's solving one direct
policy inference problem as this kind of
annealing
process so I think the beauty of this
approach is that you can do
both I like to do Direct policy
inference because I think it's it's to
me it's it feels like the right way to
go but one of the things we do in part
one and to extent demonstrate the
experiments in part two is that you can
recover like these forward
rollouts uh these classical algorithms
are special cases by only passing
messages
forwards because when you have these P
substituted uh goal observation nodes
with your mean field constraints and
everything the energy terms of those
nodes ends up being
equal to one that's what we talked about
last time and to being equal to one term
in uh the EF of a matching
policy so you can reproduce like the
forward roll out method by saying I'm
only going to pass messages in the
forward Direction I'm going to fix all
my action
variables and then I'm going to compare
all the energy terms of these little GFE
nodes and that'll reproduce you know the
exact algorithm that we've all been
using for for
years you can also do is you can add a
backwards pass what you can also do is
you can say well now I want to infer my
policy and so on and so
forth but because this is a toolbox um
it's just a thing like it's just a way
of thinking that allows you to do
different
things
um so the policy inference is not
inherent it's something that you can do
uh
if if you want
because it's just an inference
problem if you don't want to and you
have good reasons for doing something
else um you can go and do something
else um but sort of to to row back a
little bit to me this idea of reasoning
back Wass also works with sort of my
intuitions on on at least how I as a
person often operate
like I'll have some idea in mind I'll
have some goal that I want to achieve uh
which could be you know um I want to get
a PhD or I want to make a taste of
dinner or
something and then I reason backwards
well I need to do this I need to do this
I need to go and buy all the things that
I need I need to set aside time for
cooking and so on so
forth there's sort of a backwards
reasoning that if I want to go here I
need to do this this this this this
this and then there's the forward
planning all right if I am walking out
the door I need to go to there and then
there and if I keep walking I'll end up
in the right place and so there's both
components to it if you want to put sort
of a more
anthropomorphic uh intuitive spin on
it um in
practice uh what this ends up being is
just inference on the graph and if
you're an engineer it's up to you to
design uh
you know your model and your inference
procedure in a way that you end up with
the results that that you're looking
for yeah this about the policy selection
here the forward pass policy is
basically habit coming forward because
in the absence of
any aspiration or
preference policy is just well there's
various ways you can select policy still
you could select maximum Information
Gain you could select different things
but the prior on policy it the E Vector
is happen so it's kind of like that's
the starting position for what actions
are selected from
now and then it's just really
interesting to think about
this forward and backward solving which
is of of course a classic
technique but again being done in this
way where you could recover research but
it isn't Tre
search so the the the the thing you
would recover is a trajectory so an
evaluation given a particular policy the
research uh comes about when you want to
try and expand this and be smart about
uh how you uh compute things for
different given different
policies because obviously you can do
that for every single policy one at a
time and evaluate everything but that's
even more inefficient
um so what you do practically is every
time you sort of reach a branching point
you need to select a new policy you say
well I'm just going to take my
prediction here of where I would be and
I'm going to Branch off into all the
different
um know policies that I could
pursue and that'll give me sort of a new
set of of branches on my tree and then
you do the same thing as so that's how
the search tree comes about but each
sort of path through that search tree
would correspond to a forward roll out
on one of these
models
yeah you said inference is something
that you can do I want I I want to go a
little bit back um because you mentioned
this thing about the EV Vector um which
I actually think is is really really
interesting I don't know since you have
the screen share I don't know if you
have the the papers
available which papers oh of these your
two yeah yeah do you have a part one yep
all right can you go to page 33 of
course thank
you here this is the one one so if you
look here um we actually have an e
Vector sitting right on top uh as a
parameter for the um indicator
variable and what we're saying here is
just we're literally putting a prior
on uh which policy like which action to
pick at each s
stop but that's that just comes about
because we're building it out of these
little graphical building
blocks so if you wanted to you could put
a prior on E and then you could learn
e that that's absolutely something you
could do or you can say have um a shared
e with its own Dynamics so now your
habits are time
dependent and that'll be another sort of
thing that moves along at the top with
its own stat based langage everything
these are the kind of things that you
can start to
do um we used flat PRI here but you
could just as well say I'm gonna sort of
intrinsically have my agent be really
really biased
to go for the goal whatever it
checks uh we can even say I it's going
to prefer the left mode goal more than
anything in the world and that that is
something you can do but what you can do
here is you can be explicit about it
exactly how your habits work how your e
works um practice the sort of semantics
intuition you can attach to it is the
same as they they've always
been but you can start to look at well I
let look on my graph what is the thing
that I'm updating what does this like
actually sort of specifically concretely
mean and you can draw it and if you want
wanted to do something else you can you
could for instance imagine that you have
hyper PRI for E set by another
agent that just mean you extend the
graph and maybe that agent has its own
observations and so on and so forth so
then you need to attach that to the edge
that is currently clamed with E and now
you're having an agent that sort of
influences prior preferences over
policies or
habits if you want to say well now these
need to update at different rates that's
you having to mess with the schedule in
which you pass pass uh messages
sometimes you pass more than like one
agent than you do in the other but these
kind of things can be explicit now
that's to me one of the the big sort of
contributions that we wanted to put
forward with this paper is you can now
put all of this sort of directly on the
page unambiguously what exactly is
happening you notice for instance here
we have different e vectors for e a t
and e t plus1 that's also a
choice
you could for instance have these be
linked together and say they have to
share the same
thing um and that same thing now has a
prior that that's something you could do
and that would be a completely valid
graph and you could figure out how to do
inference in
that so like the idea of opening up free
form models means that
um model structure it doesn't have to be
like a b c d uh e FG and so on so forth
we can do whatever model we want like
the space is has opened
up uh for uh yeah things we can try out
with with active
inference all right I got a little bit
of a challenging question nice you're
talking about active inference and the
toolbox and that sometimes is seemingly
not what people expect they come come to
active inference or the free energy
principle looking for an account of a
human experience or of a certain
cognitive system yeah which of course
isn't to be found in the toolbox you
know any more than the blueprint or the
house itself is to be found in the
toolbox so could you from your view
going back as deep into history as you
like can you give an account of the AC
of inference toolbox what tools have
been brought in when which tools were
versioned how
which tools were deprecated
how like when would you trace the active
inference toolbox coming to existence
with
what just to get a little bit of a runup
to the state of the toolbox
today I think pretty much anyone you're
going to ask is going to have a
different answer to that there are some
sort of big fixed entities that we can
all look at the know the big one of
course being
SPM um which has been the go-to tool for
many many years and in many ways still
is because it is sort of the the battle
tested version with all the bills and
whistles that Carl himself has in large
Parts
written like that would be sort of my
my my um proposal for a a grandfather
grandmother software package for how to
do active infuence this should be the
gold
standard in my
opinion
um later on we've had uh p and DP which
was uh largely implemented by by Connor
Hines and Al chance and a couple of
other collaborators which is a great
project uh I've used it uh it's awesome
which is a python implementation of many
of the routines that exist in
SPM um so this sort of brings many of
the tools
to python instead of mlab which
is a lot more access a lot more popular
these
days
um and that will sort of to my mind be
the two big active inference
toolboxes in bias lab we have uh RX
infer which is a general purpose message
passing
toolbox so it is not
specifically an active inference toolbox
you can use it to do inference and you
can use it to do a lot of things that we
would like to do with for active
inference but it is a a message passing
sort a Bas inference engine first before
it is a of specialized active inference
tool
box which is great uh because then you
can use it to build your active
inference uh Parts uh like we did with
this uh a constraint goal observation
node that we used for the uh the
simulations we just looked at that's
using mostly stuff that is an RX and fur
and then one little node that we uh
added on that does this GF based
thing I think what what to my mind is
um the more interesting question is the
types of algorithms that have been
employed
because again and I'm I'm going to miss
some here and for everyone that I don't
mentioned uh I'm
sorry
uh but like from the original sort of
inception in 2015 of the first active
INF routines with the sort of forward
search
tree uh through
to um something like branching time
active inference or sophisticated
inference
or there been a lot of really really
interesting work with monal Tre
search uh and the whole sort of deep
active inference field that I haven't
touched on at all in in any of these
discussions because it's it's a again
it's a different
approach um there sort been an explosion
of really really interesting algorithmic
work uh on how to to do
this how to solve the the active
inference problem in a smart and
interesting way
and the things that we introduce here
are sort of more in that tradition where
we're saying uh instead of trying to
find ways to be clever about the search
tree uh or trying to sort of like the
sophisticated inference for for one is
is a really really interesting idea but
it's yeah it's a different thing instead
of be clear about the search tree we
want to introduce this backwards path so
that we can solve everything as part of
the the inference problem
um like parts of this is also something
you can find in is actually sort of an
interesting thing as well that's
mentioned in in the papers if you go and
look at uh par and friston's 2019 paper
where they introduced the generalized
free
energy uh everything is still
conditioned on a policy but the the
message passing schedule the forwards
backwards thing is actually
present and the update rules are based
on
generalize free energy so they end up
looking a lot like the update rules that
we
derive just quite interesting you can
sort of
see uh the seats of what we based this
work on quite clearly like you can you
can look at the equation side by
side um which to my mind is really
really interesting because that was sort
of the the inspiration like you have
these update rules you have this
forwards backwards thing what if we try
and do this but we come at it from uh
the point of view of doing message
passing on
graphs so I agree this is a big question
and I'm not sure I can do it justice
because there's so there's been so much
interesting work on um software and
algorithms and simulations for active
inference that whatever uh Parts I bring
up I'm bound to have missed something
um but if you if you put me on the spot
these are some of the things I would
highlight I would highlight SPM I would
highlight pmdp and later on uh know like
the message passing tool box boxes from
uh from bias lab and algorithmically I
would uh highlight the original
algorithm along with all the things we
have here like branching time onalo
sophisticated uh deep sampling based all
these kinds of things and and then put
our um work in that field more as this
is a different approach to solve the
problem uh that we're interested in when
we want to design active INF agents that
do uh do planning in interesting ways
with all the epidemics and what we
like I don't know who asked that
question um but you're right it's a
tough one it's kind of a
perennial question I mean even with some
familiarity
sometimes I find myself grasping at
how simple and clear the problem
is and how we have all the
tools to work towards it and then
there's just this interesting moment
like we know what we're interested in
and what we want to do we also know how
to do it so then like what do I do
then when when we know what we care
about and how we prefer it to be and
seemingly have no limitation on the
actual composability and the
implementation these developments happen
year by
year yeah I mean that that's always
going to be more I expect that our
method is also going to be superseded by
something that's even cleverer and even
smarter uh and I look forward to to
figuring out what it is whether we
figure it out or whether someone else
figures it out um whatever it's going to
be it's going to be awesome but I sort
of want to dwell on one of the the
points you just mentioned was this idea
that if you have what looks like a
deceptively simple problem it doesn't
mean the solution is is
simple because most of what we're doing
like 90% of everything we care about
here is really just solving Bas
rule like base rule is pretty simple to
write
down um the trick is that it's really
really really hard to
solve that's why we have whole fields of
variational inference trying to come up
with approximate solutions that are good
enough why we have uh all the like
really brilliant interesting work on
Monte Carlo samples and all these kinds
of things it's all because we know what
the problem is the problem is easy to
State problem is just solve base
solution can be really really difficult
and that's sort of where the the the
devil in the details and all the work
goes
in same is saying I just want to just
want to minimize free energy it's
easy well in paper paper edit this but
if you actually have to solve it you
need a lot more
paper easier said than done that was
probably true about the first uh rocks
being chipped into
blades just make it narrower just make
it sharper
yeah it's easy it's easy just you know
go go hunt the mammoth it's easy just
make make it lie down you can take all
the food no but but I I think this is
sort of um to me one of the really
really interesting Parts about working
in this field um that oftentimes it's
really easy to State what you
want at least for me like I have want to
you know be really really good at
updating beliefs and I want to do that
in a way that's consistent with all
these things that we like but really
when it comes down to it we just want to
update beliefs in a good
way how to do it and the details and how
the belief updating should work and
whether we should introduce all these
extra little bits and pieces like
Information Gain terms all this kind of
stuff to me that's where sort of you you
get to dig down and immerse yourself and
find all the cool things and try stuff
out and sort of that's where the work is
that that to me is is really the
exciting part but I like that I can
always understand step back and say well
I just care about doing inference
man let's look at where you left the
papers off as we kind of think about
where we
go so other than broadly summarizing all
of the acronyms and
term that's a lot
you
clamp the paper in a very interesting
way at the end yeah so what what what
would you say about this final paragraph
and like how did the different authors
perspectives um arise to result
here so this is this is actually an
interesting point
um because I think I want to come at it
in another way
um what we're trying to do here is we're
trying to provide tools uh we're trying
to build really really good tools for
doing active
inference um but as you mentioned
earlier people come to active inference
and the free energy principle for all
sorts of different reasons and for all
sorts of different
backgrounds like they maybe not everyone
is interested in in building
tools and the measure of whether our
tools are useful are whether they end up
being used by other
people if you or others pick up this
this notation and pick up these types of
message passing pick up this little
grunch and active insance
formulation then this this paper uh is
going to have the impact that we' like
it
to if nobody picks it up it's just a
cool Hammer that that keeps lying on the
shelf and sort of paradoxically um I
think one of the barriers to uptake
could
be that um a lot of the people that come
to active
inference come from say Neuroscience or
or more sort of philosophically bent
uh which is which is great like we need
everybody on on the
trrain um but they might be concerned
with other things than we
are and we didn't make any claims as to
whether this is like a biologically
plausible uh update algorithm which may
be something that uh you care a lot
about if you're a
neuroscientist don't have any claims
about how this tie is
to experience or qualia or Consciousness
or all the kinds of things that you
might be more interested in if you come
at it from sort of the more
philosophical
side
um so these
tools uh is the best we could build as
Engineers trying to make good
hammers but if what you're looking for
is not here if your um priorities lie
somewhere else
then these might not be the right ones
and like and that that's
okay um so yeah I think paradoxically
one of the things that uh could hinder
uptake and and the impact of these
papers is that the people for whom we're
building tools might care about
different things than uh what provide
with with what we
built I if you really really really want
to use a screwdriver doesn't matter that
we have the best hammer in the world
you still need a
screwdriver so because this is a a again
a tool building
exercise because this is about doing
things from an engineering point of view
uh that means they are tools for
engineers so we
don't sort of make any claims as
to biology or Consciousness or all the
other things that people are studying
under the The Heading of active INF and
the free energy principle will let
people who are are better qualified
uh and in many ways smarter in these
things than we are take care of that
what we want to do here is just say
here's a really really good Hammer uh if
that's what you want then then we got
you
covered these are really important I I I
really respect that approach I think in
terms of the otive inference ecosystem
even if there seem to be like some
barriers or hindrances associated with
really the articulation of the tool and
the and the and what it's used for um
this is how we bring more perspectives
in and if the hammer is oh yeah but then
we also included this and here's this
proprietary phone home and it only does
this type of nail and it only makes
houses all of a sudden it's it's not
really a hammer anymore it's become
welded to a larger
apparatus um and yet if the head of the
the hammer and the handle aren't
connected it's not a hammer so then it's
a fine line between like what
algorithmically in
implementation does this
essential Act of
inference
tool do what is it and then what can it
be done with it and I think actually RX
and fur and bias lab other than Burr and
you're all's incredible work over the
last years by situating within a broader
basian message passing
framework that has helped first off
bring in insights from the broader
basian inference space related to
literally fory graphs message passing
reactive message passing and so on and
then also it helps us separate
out the active inference models from
other models and there's nothing wrong
with other models if you are building a
model you find that your system of
Interest doesn't require like an active
epistemic agent for every single
component no one in the active ecosystem
is going to get mad at you for like just
doing what the situation demands and so
that's very
cool yeah again one of the the things
besides uh the new messages and
everything that that allows people to do
this uh type of message passing based
inference one of the things we wanted to
stress is that we wanted this uh
constraint FFG notation to something
that is quite easy to pick
up like it's easy to write down your
graph and if you want to do just box
standard belief propagation you don't
really have to do anything like it it'll
just it looks like 99% like a normal
Factor
graph but if you want to say do a
factorization here and there you can
like you can just draw that in by adding
a little thing for each of the uh parts
of your graph that factor together so we
want like we really stressed this should
be something that is intuitive and and
usable because we want this to be
applicable for people
who don't care about working out the
intricate s of message passing on Factor
graphs this should be a tool for
everyone uh and if you come at it from a
different background and what you want
is a nice and and clean modeling tool it
should be that for
you
what else do you think could come into
play even just totally speculatively or
arbitrarily like what do you imagine in
the preferred active toolbox even if
it's some sort of like synthetic
intelligence fantasy like what would be
the coolest thing that we could bring a
new colleague to the table and set them
down
to to me I would like um to generalize
all of these update rules that we have
derived like the general form of the GV
based messages to a point where you
don't have to worry about whether the
thing you need is is
there and then I would want it to be so
that I can give it to you or I can give
it to you know a neuroscience colleague
and I can set them down and they can
draw their graph in their C5
notation and all of that should get
translated into executable
code because then we end up in a
situation where if what you want is a
modeling language that solves your
problem you can do that you don't have
to be a technical expert and for those
of us who want to work on the technical
side of things that's a code base that
we can open up and and dig into but in
terms of a toolbox that I would like to
have have an
existence it should be something that is
really really easy to use generic
um and fast because fast as
cool do you see any difference or Reason
to build sketches in the factor graph
form or in the base graph form we know
there's an analytical relationship that
links them but is there any reason to
like work on building intuition about
Factor graphs specifically or would it
suffice to build intuition for Learners
about base graphs knowing that they can
be rendered to factor graphs later I
actually had this we had a long
conversation about this with colleague
of mine just just this week
and I think if you dig deep enough the
representation doesn't matter that much
the update rules end up becoming the
same I would say Factor graphs uh like
to me they're preferred I mean obviously
I'm biased because that's what I work on
but I also think they allow you to write
down more if I have a base graph I can
see that two variables are related
because I have a node here and I have a
node here and an edge between them with
a factor graph I can also see what the
relation is because a little Lally have
a little square that with a simple end
that tells me the
relation and also if you adopt the CFG
notation you don't just write down your
generative model you also write down uh
your constraints on Q so you can write
down
your um like the exact inference problem
that you're trying to solve and that is
something that I I'm not aware of a way
to do on on basent Networks
so to me I think there is more um
information contained in a factor
graph especially if you uh adopt
constrained
[Music]
a given base graph there's actually like
a few to one projection of factor graphs
as
constrained down to a same unconstrained
base graph and so in that sense they can
convey more information if you use the
cffg and yeah so again they don't call
it bias lab for nothing it's definitely
your fellows's uh take
but this again this is also one of
things we introduce with these these
papers um is that we identify a need to
write down more than just the generative
model if you want to be clear about
everything else you're doing because if
you don't have a graphical Rel you need
to put it in equations you need to put
in text and you need like half a page of
hieroglyphics to convey what you want to
do um and again that is a barrier if you
want this to be an accessible tool for
everyone which is one of the things that
I
want um so we augment FFG notation
specifically in a way that I'm not aware
of anyone that has done for for base
baset I might be able
to um so in that way you're right
there's more information definitely in
the CFG that in the Bas net but in
general that's also more in a factor
graph because you have to be explicit
about the relation between
variables more than you do with with at
least the versions of Bas Nets that I'm
familiar
with uh again I would say as I put on my
practical head you should use whatever
is best for for your problem whatever
you're most most comfortable with
because a lot of the math you end up
having to do comes out to be the same
like in the end it's just it's just a
picture yeah yes but there's there's
more to my mind there's more information
in especially constrained
fgs uh which means you can be really
really accurate and precise about what
you want to to do by just writing down
the
picture yeah lot of thoughts there one
great you left the door open to somebody
introducing a graphical or other than
graphical notation for Bas graph to
create a true onetoone map between Bas
graph and the constrained for graph it's
not impossible it might even be trivial
no um
and then it just makes me think of like
a learning
language that's more
broadly used Bas graphs where the nodes
and edges
have a semantics that
are equivalent to what is usually
considered as structural modeling yeah
and then you enter into the learning
language and and play space and toolbox
and then there's
this strong relationship between the
learning language again just kind of
hyperbolizing this and the engineering
implementation or
specification and then from there it's
actually anchored in message passing
like that's how we connect the Bas
graph
as sketched to the message passing is
like enter the problem into the Bas
graph if you want to enter at that point
transfer over to the cffg and then run
the messages from there however if you
wanted to you could just work directly
from the fact graph and a Bas graph
would have never had to enter into it I
I think I think that's doing a little
bit of a dis disservice to to Bas graphs
I I I have my favorites um but if you go
and look at like the original when in
Bishop papers for instance where the
original dve the VMP algorithm it's all
done for base graphs it's all done for
basent networks um so
like it's not that you can't do message
passing again this is just different
representations of a generative model um
and sometimes one is more useful uh I
find that
generically uh Factor graphs are more
useful uh when I want to work with
message passing but some other people
might might disagree um what I can say
is that uh the versions of Base graphs
that I I've seen I contain less
information than a constrained FFG
because you don't write down
uh the exact inference problems I.E the
constraints and the data points and
everything so I I wouldn't say that uh
you know there's no room for base graphs
like base graphs are great uh but I say
for the kind of work that um I'm
interested in Factor graphs feel feel
more
natural thanks for that that's great let
me ask one more question in the um in
the
graphical brain 2017 yeah paper um there
were three graph types mentioned so
we've spent a ton of time talking about
the the complementarities and the
transform abilities of of Bas graphs and
forny Factor graphs could you say a
little bit about this last form of graph
the neural network or neural
circuit
um I am
not intimately familiar with the
formalism of neural circuit
graphs uh so I don't think I can add
anything above and beyond what's here
especially if I want to make sure that I
don't say anything wrong fair enough
fair enough okay just want to check
because they're all like different
projections so but just wanted to ask I
think so if if you wanted to sort of try
and and tie a bow on it um I would say
the different graphs different graph
types and different types of graphical
notations are useful for different
things
um and whatever you need to do you
should pick what is best for the kind of
problem you're trying to
solve like if I have um if I all I'm
interested in is dependences between
variables I just know I want to know
which variables depends on which others
based that's might be the best way to
represent that and yeah that that might
be the case for the problem that that
someone is working on that this is sort
of the the central information that they
care about if I also want the relations
between the variables to be explicit and
I want to do message
passing um maybe an FFG or a cffg is a
better
representation and if I care about say
uh neural implementations maybe like a
neural circuit is um the right choice
Choice again I don't want to sort of
come out and and tell people what they
should do because I think everybody
knows what they should do better than I
do what I want to sort of propose is
that there is a a type of notation that
has these nice properties you can easily
represent the relationships between your
variables and you can represent the
constraints on Q thereby also the resing
message passing
algorithm which is something that I find
really useful uh and that I hope other
people would but if that is not the type
of problem that you're interested in and
something else works better for you you
should use something
else yeah again this is all pragmatics
this this is just a notation for how we
we want to get our ideas across clearly
and in the end what all this is really
designed to do is to communicate
information in a nice
way and you know the the the language
which we we choose to speak
in uh should reflect what we want to
say we could try you and I and have a
conversation in German but I I don't
think it would end well for either of
us at least not for me I'd be there to
hear but I wouldn't
listen or do you speak German no nor do
I there you go again we could try and
some ideas might be more expressible in
German than in English uh
but if if none of us speak it uh it's
not going to Aid Us in in transmitting
information so for this setting English
is probably the right choice of language
for other settings it might be bassets
and for other settings it might be
cfgs I have a bias to watch cfgs because
I think they are the nicest way to
represent everything that we want to do
but um for other people it might be
different and that's
okay yeah
we just did a very long unpacking of the
hammer and again as discussed if you're
not looking for that function it's not
the right language or
process I mean it's just such an
important higher order
point that that clarifies the
contribution of the paper and the
research Direction
and off up something to hopefully many
people who
will use it at least from my side only
in spoken English active inference
ontology dialect I hope that people do
use these
tools there's only seemingly a few
individuals who
are working in RX Ander making active
inference models it is very few
relatively so having that number number
broadly increase yes also training up
different kinds of synthetic
intelligences to do active inference
modeling that enriches and enlivens our
ecosystem of shared
intelligence and yeah the engineers also
need to have hands-on experience and
know and work through simpler examples
to build intuitions for larger systems
less larger systems be so far beyond our
understanding that that it's not useful
or
helpful yeah and so before we end up
wrapping up um I want to reiterate the
the invitation that I gave last time as
well if anyone out there is interested
in in working on these things uh like
hit me up I'll be happy to help you work
work out your
graphs because I think it's important
than you know measure of a tool whether
it's useful is whether it's being used
so if I can assist people in picking
this up I'll be more than happy
to
that's the most helpful and
pragmatic thing I believe I guess just
in closing
like what loads up on pragmatic value
for you what loads up on epistemic value
for you in our field as we head into
like
2024 I think I'm in the very privileged
position that I can do research for a
living uh so my pragmatic value and my
epistemic value tend to overlap a lot if
I can figure something new out
um that's pragmatic because that means I
can write a new paper and that's the
thing that I'm I'm
producing uh so I think that would be my
answer I want to try and see if I can
make this practical uh as I work it out
for more models and and try it for more
things um but it is a very privileged
position to be able to do research
uh where we basically get
to spend our days trying to figure
things out you know with with all the
admin and all the Academia things and
all the sort of other the stuff that
goes on but at the end of the day uh I
do get to spend a large chunk of my time
figuring things out and that is really
really nice so the epistemic and the
pragmatic value tend to
overlap which is is nice
well thank you it's a beautiful
sentiment so it was a great
Series this is
really a a
mega Tech Tree direction
for the actm ecosystem and Beyond so
good luck with your continued work and
play and research Magnus it was
awesome thanks I had a a blast coming on
here it's been some really really great
discussions and for those of you
participate in chat um got some hard
questions that's good yes and it will
continue in The Institute
Discord excellent I I'll see you there
see you Magnus
bye